[MUSIC]
[음악]
Okay, so the issue we're facing here with this crazy 13th order polynomial fit
이런 13차 다항식의 문제를
is something called overfitting.
과적합이라고 합니다
So in particular, what we've done is we've taken a model and really,
지금까지 모델을 관찰 결과에
really, really honed in to our actual observations, but
딱 들어맞도록 끼워맞췄지만
it doesn't generalize well to thinking about new predictions.
새로운 예측으로 일반화되지는 않습니다
And so the issues actually go beyond just making really crazy predictions.
예측이 틀리는 것보다 더 큰 문제도 있는데
And we're gonna discuss this in a lot more detail in the regression course.
회귀 강의에서 자세히 다루겠습니다
But I wanna mention that this is a real problem with any machine learning model or
하지만 이건 어떤 기계학습 모델이나
statistical model that you might consider.
통계 모델에서든 마주칠 수 있는 문제라는 점을 밝혀둡니다
So in these cases, we wanna fit a model to data, but
이 경우 데이터에 모델을 맞추고는 싶지만
we don't want that model to be so specified exactly to the one data set that
모델이 그 한 데이터 세트에만 딱 맞아서
we have that it doesn't generalize well to new observations we might get.
다른 관찰 결과로 일반화되지 않는 상황도 원치 않습니다
Okay, so let's go back to this 13th order degree polynomial fit.
다시 13차 다항식으로 돌아가보죠
And a question is, do we actually believe this?
이게 정말 타당할까요?
Do we believe that this might be a reasonable fit to the data?
이게 데이터에 맞는 선이라고 확신하시나요?
And I think as I alluded to before, probably not.
제가 암시했듯이 아마 아닐 것입니다
So although it minimizes the residual sum of squares,
잔차제곱합은 최소화할지라도
it ends up leading to very bad predictions.
예측은 빗나가게 됩니다
Because I'm sitting here and thinking, well, this quadratic fit that we had,
왠지 여기 이 회귀곡선이 비록
even though it didn't minimize my residual sum of squares as much as that 13th
13차 다항식만큼이나 잔차제곱합을 최소화하지 못하더라도
order polynomial, it still, my gut feeling is, somehow this is a better model.
제 감으로는 나은 모델인 것 같습니다
Okay, so a question is, what's going on here, and
그러니까 중요한 점은
how do we think about choosing the right model order or model complexity?
어떤 모델 차수, 모델 복잡도가 적절하냐는 것입니다
Well, what we want, is we want good predictions.
물론 원하는 건 뛰어난 예측이죠
Of course, that's what we're aiming for.
그게 목표입니다
But we can't actually observe the future.
하지만 미래를 미리 당겨볼 수는 없죠
Right, so we can't actually observe that prediction that we want to make and
그렇기에 미리 예측을 검증해서 잘했는지 알 수는 없고
say did we do a good job or not until we actually go ahead and do it.
결과가 나와야 비로소 알게 되는거죠
So when we're thinking about choosing our model,
모델을 선택할 때
somehow we have to work just with the data that we have.
당장 손에 쥐고 있는 데이터만으로 결론을 내야 합니다
So how can we think about trying to choose a good model in this case?
좋은 모델을 선택하기 위해 뭘 할 수 있을까요?
Well, what we can do is we can think about simulating predictions.
예측을 시뮬레이션해볼 수 있겠죠
So we're gonna take our data set that we have,
데이터 세트를 가지고
and we're gonna remove some of the houses.
몇몇 주택을 제거합니다
So those are the grayed-out houses here.
회색처리된 주택들입니다
These are gonna be removed temporarily.
잠시 없다고 가정하죠
And we're gonna fit our model on the remaining houses.
남은 주택들로 모델에 맞출 겁니다
So all of these guys we're gonna use to fit our model using
이 주택과 이전에 논했던 방법론을 써서
exactly the kind of methods that we talked about before.
모델에 맞출 겁니다
And then what we're gonna do is we're gonna predict.
그런 다음 예측을 하죠
So I'll go through an erase these x's now and put question marks.
여기 이 x를 지우고 물음표를 붙입니다
And say from the model that I just learned on the circled houses,
동그라미 친 주택을 학습한 모델로
what values do I predict for these question marks?
물음표 친 주택에 대해 어떤 예측이 가능한가?
And then I can compare to the actual observed values,
그리고 실제 수치와 비교하는데
because these houses are in my data set.
이 주택들은 데이터 세트에 있기 때문이죠
Okay, so I can use this as a proxy for doing the types of
아직 수집하지 않은 데이터 예측을
real predictions that I wanna do on data that I haven't yet collected.
대체할 수 있습니다
Of course, this type of method only is gonna work well if I have enough
물론 이런 방법은 충분한 관찰결과가
observations to think about fitting on versus testing my predictions on.
있어서 모델 설정과 예측에 적절히 할당할 수 있어야 하죠
Okay, so let's introduce a little bit of terminology.
용어 소개를 잠시 해보죠
Well, the houses that we use to fit our model, we call that the training set.
모델 설정을 위한 주택들을 훈련 세트라고 부릅니다
And the houses that we're using as a proxy for
예측을 위해 따로 빼놓은 주택을
our predictions, those that we're holding out, we call the test set.
테스트 세트라고 부르죠
Okay, so let's dig a little bit more into how we're gonna do this analysis.
이제 이 분석을 어떻게 할 것인지 자세히 알아보죠
And the first thing that we can do is look at something called the training error.
먼저 훈련 오류를 살펴봅시다
So we're gonna examine every house in our test data set.
테스트 데이터 세트에 있는 모든 주택을 검사합니다
So let's look at this red color here.
빨간색을 쓰죠
So all of our training houses are represented
훈련 세트에 포함된 모든 주택은
with these blue circles here, and these are the only houses
파란 동그라미로 표시되어 있고
we're gonna look at when we're thinking about defining our training error.
훈련 오류를 정의할 때 이것들만 봅니다
So in particular,
특히
we're gonna look at what are the errors that we make on these houses?
이 주택들에 대한 오류가 얼마나 되는지 살펴봅니다
So this is just the residual sum of squares on the houses in our training
단순히 훈련 데이터 세트의 잔차제곱합이 되는데
data set, and that's called the training error.
이걸 훈련 오류라고 부릅니다
So in particular, the training error looks exactly like what we had for
훈련 오류는 잔차제곱합 계산과
our residual sum of squares calculation, but
거의 같은데 훈련 데이터 세트에 있는
we're only including the houses that are present in our training data set.
주택들만 포함시키는 게 다릅니다
Okay, so then for any given model, such as a linear fit through the data,
회귀직선, 회귀곡선, 어떤 모델이든 간에
quadratic fit, or so on, what we can do is we can think about estimating our model
훈련 오류를 최소화하는 모델 파라미터를
parameters as those that minimize the training error.
예측하는 것이 핵심이죠
So that's equivalent to what we talked about before of minimizing the residual
이건 전에 말씀드린 잔차제곱합 최소화와
sum of squares.
일치합니다
But again, here we're only looking at the houses in our training data set.
하지만 다시 강조하자면 훈련 데이터 세트에 있는 주택들만 본다는 게 다른 점이죠
Okay, so then that's how we get our estimated w hat,
예측 모델 파라미터 w 모자는
our estimated model parameters.
이렇게 구합니다
But then what we wanna do is we wanna take these estimated model parameters, and
하지만 이 예측 모델 파라미터가
we wanna say how good are we doing?
적절한지 어떻게 알 수 있나요?
And remember what we said, what we're gonna do,
아까 말씀드렸듯이
is we're gonna look at our held out observations, okay?
따로 빼놓은 관찰결과를 살펴본다고 했었죠?
So here, these gray circles are the houses that are in our test set.
이 회색 동그라미가 테스트 세트에 있는 주택들입니다
So these are houses that were not used to fit this model.
모델 설정에 사용하지 않은 주택들이죠
And we're gonna say how well are we predicting these actual house sales?
실제 주택 판매 가격 예측이 잘 됐는지 보겠습니다
Okay, and so what were our predictions?
예측을 어떻게 했지요?
Well, remember when we thought about making a prediction,
예측할 때는
we just used the value of the fit, so just the point on the line.
회귀곡선의 수치, 그러니까 곡선 상의 점을 이용했습니다
So to assess how well we're predicting these held-out observations,
따로 빼놓은 테스트 데이터 예측에 대한 평가를 하자면
our test data, we're gonna look at something that, again,
또 다시
looks exactly like residual sum of squares.
잔차제곱합 같은 걸 계산하게 됩니다
But it's called our test error,
테스트 오류라고 하는데
where we take these estimated model parameters w hat, and we sum
예측 모델 파라미터 w 모자에 테스트 데이터 세트에 있는
over our residual sum of squares over all houses that are in our test data set.
모든 주택의 잔차제곱합을 더합니다
Okay, so that's our test error.
이게 테스트 오류죠
But what we can think about is we can think about how does test error and
테스트 오류와 훈련 오류가
training error vary as a function of the model complexity?
모델 복잡도의 함수로 어떻게 변화하나요?
[MUSIC]
[음악]